PO Box 7965 Ann Arbor MI 48107-7965 (772) 332 I319 **☎** +1 (734) 926 9427  $\bowtie$  alton.b.h.worthington@gmail.com abhworthington.com abhworthington

# Alton B.H. Worthington

## Summary

Professional Project management, teaching, methodological consulting (internal and client-facing), document and workflow management, Experience statistical programming, general project problem-solving, basic computer programming

Research International and comparative political economy, trade economics, quantitiative research methods (design and implementa-

Expertise tion), game theory, research design

### Education

current Political Science, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, PhD Candidate.

With focus on International Relations, Comparative Politics, Research Methodology and Formal Modeling, and Economics

Economics and Political Science, Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, BA.

Graduated with Honors

#### Doctoral thesis

title MNCs, NTBs, and New Protectionism: Industrial Protection Coalitions in an Era of Global Capital

William R. Clark (TAMU), Andrew M. Kerner (UM), Iain G. Osgood (UM)

description

The dissertation explains the conditional rise of non-tariff protections as tariffs declined in postwar global economy. The core claim is that global capital flows created political incentives which changed the politics of protectionism in many countries. I advance a new typology of "market access barriers", an improvement over the existing tariff/NTM framing which clarifies, both empirically and theoretically, the effect of trade-distorting policies. From this, I develop a model of industrial coalitional politics in support of or opposition to different policy options. I present empirical support for hypothesized divergence across industries and countries in the nature of protection using a new dataset developed from the UNCTAD TRAINS database and other sources.

# Experience

#### Teaching/Research

2009-present Graduate Student Instructor, *University of Michigan*, Ann Arbor, MI.

Instructor for undergraduate- and graduate-level classes in Political Science and International Studies

- Introduction to International Relations
  - 2009-2013 Served as assistant instructor, responsible for grading, ensuring student engagement w/material in international security, international political economy, and international organizations, and Administrative Assistant for other student instructors and professor
  - 2016 Instructor of record, responsible for all aspects of instruction, including lecturing, assessment design, and ensuring student understanding of core concepts and data in international security, political economy, and organizations
- Introduction to International Studies
  - 2015 Instructor of record, responsible for all aspects of instruction in course on international security, international politics and economics, the global environment, and comparative cultures
- Mathematics for Social Scientists and Introduction to Formal Theory
  - 2011-2013 Assistant instructor for graduate course in mathematics (Scalar and Matrix Algebra, Differential and Integral Calculus, Probability Theory, Set Theory) and game theory/formal modeling (social choice theory and non-cooperative game theory), responsible for grading, periodic assessments, one-on-one and group tutoring
- o Intermediate Statistical Methods for Political Scientists
  - 2014 Assistant instructor for graduate course in multivariate statistics and causal inference, taught programming in R alongside fundamentals of (& applied) statistical methods for social scientists, responsible for grading, periodic assessments, one-on-one and group tutoring

2009-present Research Assistant, Various Faculty, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI.

Provided general research assistance and specific quantitative analysis/game theory support for research projects, including

- o "Behavioral Genetics and Foreign Policy Cues", with Allan C. Stam
  - Behavioral genetics/structural equation modeling of public opinion survey data from twin study, R/OpenMx programming, writing, research
- o "Combat Environment and Long-term Costs of War", with Allan C. Stam
  - Behavioral genetics/structural equation modeling of panel data of health outcomes from historical twin study of Vietnam-era Veterans, R/OpenMx programming, writing, research, management of protected/sensitive data
- "Pension Underfunding Among the States", with Robert Mickey
  - Developed database of public pension fund liabilities from existing incomplete panel data, basic research, econometric analysis, archival research (nationwide) and aggregation of archival sources into quantitative database for future analysis
- "Distributive Politics under Authoritarian Conditions: Does Goods Delivery Generate Positive Evaluations of Government Performance?", with Anne Pitcher
  - Performed statistical analysis and prepared presentation/visualization of results of public opinion survey related to public goods
    provision in Angola, survey validity testing, prepared several supplemental reports on short notice in response to stakeholder
    requests to PI
- o "A Theory of Creole Genesis", with Jinho Baik, Marlyse Baptista, and Ken Kollman
  - Modified and debugged agent-based model (simulation) of language evolution written in C++, responsible for running simulation iterations (Python), and organizing, summarizing, and presenting simulation output, writing about model and results for mathematics/linguistics/political science/complex systems audiences
- o "Regional Parties and Decentralization", with Ken Kollman
  - Designed and estimated multivariate dynamic models on panel data of elections and institutions across the world, data visualization
     including GIS mapping, statistical model adaptation, data management

#### Professional

2014-2015 Independent Consultant, Claes Fornell International Group, Ann Arbor, MI.

Served as special consultant/advisor to Director of Customer Analytics at CFI Group.

- o General consulting for transition from proprietary statistical software to R (and related applications) statistical language
- Provided client-specific analysis, building on existing analysis framework and introducing new methods
- Developed interactive data visualization and analysis tools in Shiny
- Provided analysis and tools for better use of existing data to generate new insights for clients

Nov. 2014 Visiting Scholar, Ural Federal University, Ekaterinburg, Sverdlovsk Oblast, Russia.

Consulted in design of a program in "Social and Behavioral Research" in Department of Public Administration and Entrepreneurship

- Developed course (and proposed course program) in US-style social science research methods w/focus on hypothesis testing, positivist
  methods, and research design
- o Collaborated with local faculty and staff to meet Russian Federal educational requirements in course design and documentation
- Gave impromptu lectures on methods of positivist research design and implementation to groups of Masters-level students and UrFU faculty
- o Collected and disseminated training resources (articles, texts, technical resources) for use by local faculty in course program
- Presented course proposal to faculty body and department administration for approval
- Worked remotely w/ faculty during final preparation of course (Dec 2014-May 2015)

#### Other/Unpaid

2012-2014 Maintenance Director, Sandhill Soaring Club, Gregory, MI.

Served as volunteer maintenance manager for fleet of airplanes and gliders for soaring co-op/educational club, responsible for FAA-related documentation and bookkeeping, coordinated outside contractors and club members for maintenance efforts, managed budgeting/scheduling of fleet upkeep

2006-2008 Team/Project Manager/Advisor, Rutgers Formula Racing, New Brunswick, NJ.

Various management/supervisory responsibilities related to design, construction, and tuning of a Formula SAE race car. Manager/supervisor of related student organization, responsible for managing fund-raising, stakeholder outreach, documentation, logistics, and University interface with respect to organization.

# Grant-funded Research Projects

2012 Rackham Spring-Summer Research Grant, "The Political Sources of Global Income Inequality", w/William R. Clark.

This project explained the divergence in economic growth and incomes in the "global North" and "global South" as the consequence of specific barriers to economic openness beginning in the 19th century. The effect of the interaction of political institutions (democratization) and factor abundance (labor vs capital abundance) was tested using a new dataset on institutions, factor abundance, tariff and capital controls, and economic flows developed from a variety of historical sources and integrating other existing datasets.

Roy Pierce Scholars Fund Award, "Calling the Shot: The Political Economy of Inflation Targeting", w/Andrew M. Kerner. This project developed a theory of the conditional effectiveness of inflation targeting policies in moderating inflation and tested it using a new database of inflation targeting policies and other monetary institutions in economies within and beyond the OECD.

Bobbe Jon Bridge Research Award, "Say Anything: Central Bank Independence, Coordinated Wage Bargaining, and Monetary Policy Transparency in Developed Economies", w/Robert J. Franzese.

This project expanded on Franzese's previous work on Central Bank Independence, Coordinated Wage Bargaining, and inflation to introduce the effect of central bank transparency on moderating inflation above and beyond central bank independence.

## Computing skills

Statistical

R (advanced, including visualization and interaction), Stata

Document

Software

L<sup>A</sup>TEX(advanced, including Beamer), Office/Open-source Office Alternative

Creation Collaboration

Git/Github, Dropbox/Box, Google app suite

Programming C++, HTML (basic), Python (basic), Javascript (basic)

## References

#### Professional/Research

- o Kenneth W. Kollman Director, o Shaun C. McGirr Lead Data Scien-UM Center for Political Studies kkollman@umich.edu
- Dept. of Political Science rmickey@umich.edu

#### Personal/Collaborators

- tist Cox Automotive UK Shaun.McGirr@coxauto.co.uk
- o Robert Mickey Professor, UM o Meredith L. Blank Pre-Doctoral Fellow - ISCS-GWU merlaurenblank@gmail.com
  - O Logan S. Casey Research Analyst -Harvard Opinion Research Program lcasey@hsph.harvard.edu

#### Other References

Academic and additional references, as well as phone numbers for references here, available upon request.